Armin Scheler Papers
Armin Scheler Papers
1932-1965
Scheler, Armin, 1901-
0.5 linear ft.
Papers of the German-born American sculptor. Collection contains incoming and outgoing correspondence (1949-1965); exhibition catalogs (1939-1965); photographs (1932-1962); and manuscripts (1945-1964).
149567
Biographical History
Armin Scheler (1901-) was a German-born American sculptor and teacher. The bulk of his career was spent in New York and Lousiana.
Born on May 20, 1901 in Sonneberg, Germany, Scheler received his professional preparation and education in the art schools in Munich, Germany. He received his first recognition when he was living in Switzerland in the years 1923 to 1924.
In 1926, Scheler came to the United States and became a naturalized citizen. From 1926 to 1936 he lived in and around New York City where he worked first in the capacity of industrial designer and then as an assistant to various sculptors in their New York studios. In 1936, he became a free-lance sculptor, and set up his own studio in New Rochelle, New York.
Scheler's work has been exhibited at the Whitney Museum of American Art, Corcoran Gallery of Art in Washington, D.C., National Academy of Design, Dallas Museum of Fine Art, Philadelphia Museum of Art, and Isaac Delgado Museum of Fine Arts.
Scheler joined the faculty of the School of Fine Arts at Louisiana State University in 1942, eventually rising to become head of the department. In addition to his art, he was a regular contributor to The Magazine of Art, Art in Modern America, and The Southwest Review.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Armin Scheler Papers consist of biographical material, correspondence (incoming and outgoing, filed separately), subject files (exhibition notices and photographs of Scheler's sculpture), and manuscripts of articles by Scheler.
Arrangement of the Collection
Incoming correspondence is arranged alphabetically by sender and outgoing correspondence arranged chronologically. Subject files are arranged alphabetically by topic; within that, exhibition catalogs are arranged chronologically and photographs of Scheler's work alphabetically by title of the work. Manuscripts are arranged alphabetically by title.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Sculptors; Scheler, Armin, 1901-; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; German Americans.; Sculptors -- United States.; Sculpture, American.; Sculpture, American -- 20th century.; Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Artists.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Incoming
    - Arts and Activities magazine, 1959 (Box 1)
    - B, 1951; 1963 (Box 1)
    - California, University of, 1950 (Box 1)
    - Dallas Museum of Fine Arts, 1951 (Box 1)
    - Isaac Delgado Museum of Art, 1951; 1957,; 1961 (Box 1)
    - Kansas State University, 1961 (Box 1)
    - Louisiana State University, 1950; 1960,; 1964,; undated (Box 1)
    - Meadville Theological School, The, 1957; 1959 (Box 1)
    - Oklahoma Art Center, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
    - Oklahoma University, 1960 (Box 1)
    - Philadelphia Museum of Art, 1949; 1960,; undated (Box 1)
    - San Francisco Museum of Art, 1960 (Box 1)
    - State of Louisiana Art Commission, 1962 (Box 1)
    - United States Government, undated (Box 1)
    - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1952; undated (Box 1)
  - Outgoing
    - Miscellaneous, 1950-1955; 1959-1961,; 1964-1965 (Box 1)
- Subject files
  - Exhibition catalogs, 1939; 1947,; 1949,; 1952,; 1957-1962,; 1964-1965,; undated (Box 1)
  - Photographs of work
    - "Ascending Bird", 1962 (Box 1)
    - "Bathing Boy", 1938 (Box 1)
    - "Bird with Necklace", 1952 (Box 1)
    - "Cane Cutters, The" (U.S. Federal Government Office Building, New Orleans, Louisiana), 1940-1941 (Box 1)
    - "Composition", 1943 (Box 1)
    - "Dream of A Petal", 1950 (Box 1)
    - "Elder and the Younger, The", 1945 (Box 1)
    - "Embrace", 1943 (Box 1)
    - "Eve", 1932 (Box 1)
    - "Fledgling", 1958 (Box 1)
    - From an album of photos, undated (Box 1)
    - From a one-man show, 1952 (Box 1)
    - "Generation", undated (Box 1)
    - "Girl Reading", 1935-1936 (Box 1)
    - "Little Petal", 1951 (Box 1)
    - "Little Phoenix", 1962 (Box 1)
    - "Militant Bird", 1961 (Box 1)
    - "Nest of Birds", 1960 (Box 1)
    - "Noah's Boomerang", 1952 (Box 1)
    - "Petal-Horizon", 1948 (Box 1)
    - "Prophet and His Seed, The", 1947 (Box 1)
    - Relief (and Details of Same) for United States Post Office, Evanston, Illinois, 1937-1938 (Box 1)
    - "Seated Girl", 1943 (Box 1)
    - "Sebastian, 1944", 1946 (Box 1)
    - "Shrike, The", 1955 (Box 1)
    - "Vogelsang", 1955 (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - Articles by
    - "Inbetweeners or Castaways, The", undated (Box 1)
    - "I Noted In Passing That", undated (Box 1)
    - "Of Purpose", undated (Box 1)
    - "One Teacher's Creed", 1945 (Box 1)
    - "Reference", 1938; 1944 (Box 1)
    - "Speaking for Myself Again", 1964 (Box 1)
    - "To All Who Wish to Concern Themselves", 1960 (Box 1)
    - "To Him Who Wishes to Concern Himself", undated (Box 1)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 1)
  - Article by Scheler with quotes by others
    - "Foreword", 1963 (Box 1)